Start with hand hygiene and introduce yourself.
Confirm the patient's identity, then explain the examination and gain consent to perform it.
Take a few seconds to observe the periorbita, eyelids and the eyes themselves, commenting on any positive or relevant negative findings.
The next step is to perform the fundal reflex test to assess for mediopacity.
Set the arclight by clicking the button three times for the brightest light, and then move the lens rack to the top so there's no lens power.
With the arc light prepared, dim the lights in the room, and at arm's
length, look through
the sighthole.
I asked the patient to look at the light, observing both eyes at the same time.
The light should reflect from the fundus back through the pupils, looking symmetrically
bright with similar colour.
Any asymmetry suggests an abnormality such as corneal scar, cataract, blood in the vitreus,
or a retinal tumor.
Next examine the back of the eye.
I asked the patient to fix on a target in the distance.
Use your right hand and right eye to examine their right eye and your
left for their left.
Start with your feet close to the patient and lean back, identify the fundal reflex and
follow this moving in on a path 10 to 15 degrees temporal on the horizontal.
When you're close to the eye the optic disc should come into view, going closer still
and you'll get a wider and more stable view.
Comment on how distinct the margin of the disc is, the colour of the
neurorectal rim and the
cup to disc ratio.
Then look for other signs along the four major branches of the retinal
vessels.
Finish by asking the patient to look into the light to bring the centre of the macula
called the fovea into view.
In a non-dilator die this will cause the people to constrict
and you will lose the view.
In a dilated pupil the fovea can be seen as a slightly darker
zone with a pinpoint reflection.
Repeat this examination on the other eye.
After the
examination, thank the patient, summarise your findings and repeat hand hygiene.
Please have a look at our other University of St Andrew's Arklight project videos.